A Guide to the Graham, Tate and related families Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #9232-p
Graham, Tate and related families Papers 1844 (1920-1990)
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
9232-p
ca. 1,000 items
Agnes Graham Sanders Riley
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the Library from Mrs. Agnes Graham Sanders Riley of Lexington, Kentucky, on June 21, 1990.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 1,000 items, 1844 (1920-1990), including correspondence, personal and professional papers, genealogy and local history research files, photographs, and printed material, pertaining to the Graham, Sanders, and Tate families, and Wythe County, Virginia. Among the correspondence are letters, 1955-1956, from Agnes Graham Sanders Riley while in South Africa, and letters from Andrew Trigg Sanders and Friel Tate Sanders while serving as U. S. Army officers during World War II.
Letters, 1955-1956, written by Agnes Graham Sanders Riley from South Africa reveal cultural customs, including labor, social, educational, and religious; life for the American family; and limited historical and political news (due to censorship). Edward Thompson Wailes, Ambassador to the Union of South Africa, is mentioned in letters of August 21 & 25 and September 6, 1955 and February 9, 1956. Park Riley's education and the school system are discussed in letters of September 2 & 6 and October 31, 1955 and January 13, 18, & 21, 1956. There is mention of the Eisenhowers and/or U. S. politics in letters of September 27, October 18, and November 23 & 29, 1955.
Highlights of the letters from South Africa are as follows:
1955 Aug 1 & 3 --Onboard R.M.S. "Queen Mary" and arrival in London, England
1955 Aug 16 --Near Capetown, Cape of Good Hope, South Africa, family news
1955 Aug 21 -- Pretoria, S.A., arrived and taken to meet the American Consul, invitation for dinner at the home of the American Ambassador who graduated in Herbert's class at Oak Ridge, legislature in session putting hardship on housing conditions
1955 Aug 25 -- Pretoria, S.A., dined with Ambassador Wailes, government in session
1955 Sep 2 -- Pretoria, S.A., son Park's school attire, school run by Christian Brothers
1955 Sep 6 -- Pretoria, S.A., to Margaret Faust, Ambassador and Mrs. Wailes, their own 20th wedding anniversary on August 25, British-Boer division, problems of school and housing, private school run by Christian Brothers, some customs and views in South Africa
1955 Sep 8 -- Pretoria, S.A., strict customs, a visit to a Presbyterian church, a school house in Pretoria in which Churchill was held prisoner during the British-Boer War
1955 Sep 21 -- Pretoria, S.A., attended a memorial for the Battle of Britain at the Cathedral, a meeting of the Prebyterian Church of the Province of South Africa
1955 Sep 27 -- Pretoria, S.A., concern for Eisenhower and his illness and burdens
1955 Oct 12 -- Pretoria, S.A., hotel life, being invited to so many social functions, Herbert being a public figure and probably being transferred to the University of Cape Town
1955 Oct 18 -- Pretoria, S.A., politics -- [William Averell] Harriman, weather, meeting people from Holland
1955 Oct 24 -- Pretoria, S.A., beauty of jacaranda trees, city celebrating its 100th anniversary, weather
1955 Oct 31 -- Pretoria, S.A., Park's school work, Herbert going to Rhodes University
1955 Oct-Nov -- Livingstone, North Rhodesia, visiting Victoria Falls, [David] Livingstone's discovery of the falls in 1855, wild animals in the game reserve
1955 Nov 11 -- Pretoria, S.A., Herbert at Rhodes University in Grahamstown, English part of the Union
1955 Nov 17 -- Pretoria, S.A., centenary celebration--bazaars for charity
1955 Nov 23 -- Pretoria, S.A., moving to Cape Town soon, Mamie's [Eisenhower] troubles
1955 Nov 29 -- Pretoria, S.A., Anglican Church service for Americans, Eisenhower's recovery, voting age in Kentucky being lowered to 18
1955 Dec 4 -- Pretoria, S.A., life in South Africa--winter clothes being packed, Herbert's talk at the South African National Laboratory, America-South Africa amateur baseball game
1955 Dec 11 -- Durban, S.A., traveling to Cape Town, from Johannesburg to Durban was a 6,000 foot drop
1955 Dec 14-16 -- East London, S.A., travelled through native reserve country; Port Elizabeth, S.A., snake farm, pineapple and banana farms, visiting baseball team from America
1955 Dec 22 -- Cape Town, S.A., temporary living arrangements near the University
1955 Dec 29 -- Cape Town, S.A., Christmas celebration at home and church service
1955 Dec 31 -- Cape Town, S.A., concern for mother
1956 Jan 6 -- Cape Town, S.A., concern for mother, Park's new friends
1956 Jan 8 -- Cape Town, S.A., Nannie Graham's birthday, congregational church service
1956 Jan 13 -- Cape Town, S.A., saw Governor General ride to open parliament, problems finding a school for Park due to overcrowded conditions
1956 Jan 18 -- Cape Town, S.A., mails, university president's wife got Park in a good school--Anglican
1956 Jan 2 -- Cape Town, S.A., Park's school, less American friends here than in Pretoria
1956 Jan 25 -- Cape Town, S.A., view from window of Table Mountain, the University, and Rhodes Memorial, invited to Parliament--beautiful buildings
1956 Feb 1 -- Cape Town, S.A., plans to return home, toured Cape Town, a beautiful city
1956 Feb 9 -- Cape Town, S.A., Ambassador and Mrs. Wailes in town and inviting them to dinner
1956 Feb 13 -- Cape Town, S.A., went onboard British luxury liner Coronia, had luncheon in the dining room of the Houses of Parliament (former student's uncle a member of Parliament)
1956 Feb 20 -- Cape Town, S.A., comparison of people in Pretoria and Cape Town, attended the celebration of the World Day of Prayer
1956 Feb 27 -- Cape Town, S.A., plans to leave for home, bought plants to send to Kentucky
1956 Mar 7 -- Cape Town, S.A., heard bad news about Charlie Graham, careful not to comment on South African politics
1957 --Typed manuscript: "The Republic of South Africa" by Agnes S. Riley. History accompanying Herbert's slide presentation.
During 1942-1947, Andrew Trigg Sanders(1910-) wrote about life in North Africa during World War II, general news about the war and conditions, and family and other news from home. On February 27, 1942, he wrote about camp life [probably in North Africa]. During October through December 1942, he was at Camp Pickett, Virginia, the location of new headquarters. During 1943, he wrote from North Africa. There are letters revealing his work in the supply section and with the Special Services branch, planning athletic and entertainment programs, and commenting on Arab lifestyles (March 16); mentioning news of a friend "Jean," who had her picture taken with Walt Disney and that two Virginia medical units are nearby (April 24); discussing organizational changes and inquiring about rationing at home (May 17); referring to his teaching school, a class for 2nd lieutenants and enlisted men (July 9); remarking that recent developments make it harder to identify friend or enemy (October 3); and, relating news of the death of young Graham, son of Dave and Verna and the sale of the Graham farm (October 3, November 10). From November 1943 until October 30, 1945, he was in Italy. On November 27, 1943, he wrote, after arriving, that the people and the country were quite different than in North Africa, that fruits and nuts were plentiful but that there was a shortage of other foods, that the land was more fertile but that the destruction greater, and that the people were easier to talk to than the French. On May 29, 1944, he reported that he was doing special work away from his unit and having a chance to see more of the country. By June 23, 1944, he returned to his unit and found many changes, which he also mentioned in his letter of August 18, 1944. In his letter of September 19, 1944, he speculated as to when the war would be over and whether they would go to the Pacific; mentioned casting his vote for Roosevelt; and being sent to Rome in charge of a group of men going there to rest, where he got the chance to tour certain points of interest. There are several letters following that discuss general news about the war and his family at home. On May 9, 1945, he was anxious to hear about the point system and expected to remain in Naples for six or eight months. And, on May 25, he wrote that service troops would be the last to return home. On July 12, 1945, he wrote that they are now preparing equipment for the East, that there were 3,000 soldiers, civilians, and POWs in one shop, and that he was now executive officer. Through the end of 1945, his letters are filled with hopes of returning home. There is also a letter, January 31, 1947, concerning a training session re: crude petroleum.
Letters, 1926-1947, from Edwin Hanson Sanders(1871-1948), and related correspondence, discuss family and business matters. There is a letter, April 5, 1929, from Shipton Kincannon Curran Sanders(his mother) to William E. Fulton concerning family news. A letter of August 18, 1933, from Rev. H. G. Allen discusses the death of Shipton K. C. Sanders. Edwin Hanson Sanders wrote from the Department of Agriculture and Immigration, discussing breed of cattle and mentioning the effect of the war or prospects for war on farm products (November 10, 1939); and, giving a comparison of the business boom during the Spanish-American War, World War I, and the current one, mentioning the growing business activity at Radford with some eight thousand working, and commenting on low patriotism, partly due to salary conflicts.
Letters, 1924-1925, from Edwin Hanson Sanders, Jr. discuss life at Hampden-Sidney. Letters of March 1 and 22 refer to his bid to an honorary fraternity [ The 13 Society], which chose "all round good men," who were then only known as members during their senior year.
Letters, 1939-1946, from Friel Tate Sanders(1915-1959) cover chiefly the period during World War II. During February 1943 through April 1945, he was stationed in China. On March 20, he wrote that he arrived at his assigned post and was living in a private home and described life there. His letter of July 20, 1943 mentioned that the foods were similar, such as new potatoes, beans, tomatoes, corn, chicken, and watermelon. On July 31, 1944, he has heard good news and broadcasts about the Germans and Japanese. On November 28, 1944, he wrote that he has been moved to a new station; and, on March 20, 1945, he wrote that he is awaiting orders to go home. He wrote, from Miami Beach, Florida, on May 18, 1945, that the war was over, that he has finished processing and is awaiting a new assignment, that some materials are being released, such as tires, and that there is a possibility of an increase in gas allowance. During June through August 1945, he wrote from Stuttgart, Arkansas, concerning work and continuing studies under the G.I. Bill. Letters of October 31 and December 19, 1946, are concerned with his marriage to Nelda Rose Hunter.
Other correspondents or topics of interest are: " Hollins College" folder -- E. Lee Trinkle(May 24, 1924); Eleanor "Siddy" Wilson(October 20, 1930); Bessie Carter Randolph, President of Hollins College(January 10 and March 5, 1938). "Kentucky, University of" folder -- John Canaday(January 30, 1964), Mills E. Godwin, Jr.(November 13, 1969). "Personal Papers" folders -- Leslie Hellerman re method of testing stability of diazomium compounds (February 7, 1935); wedding announcements and photographs (August 21, 1935); war ration book (1943); John A. Logan, Jr., President of Hollins College(April 5, 1971 and June 26, 1974); W. R. Chitwood(December 2, 1974); Paula P. Brownlee, President of Hollins College(July 18, 1981, December 4, 1983, and May 5, 1986); and, an obituary/memorial to Herbert Parkes Riley(March 22, 1988). "Southwest Virginia" folder -- W. Edwin Hemphill(January 21, 1964); Ralph McGill(September 29, 1967); William H. Dumont(July 9, 1968); John Melville Jennings(January 14, 1970); W. R. Chitwood(March 2, 1971; November 24, 1975; June 20 & 28, 1985); William M. E. Rachel(1971-1972); Harrison E. Salisbury(August 20, 1973); and Paul C. Nagel(September 23, 1985).
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Letters from Nannie Montgomery Graham, 1908, 1914 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from William Tate Graham, 1936-1950 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Agnes Graham Sanders Riley in South Africa, 1955-1956 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Andrew Trigg Sanders, chiefly during World War II, 1941-1947 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Edwin Hanson Sanders, and related correspondence, 1926-1947 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Edwin Hanson Sanders, Jr., 1924-1925 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Elizabeth Graham Sanders, 1945-1956 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Friel Tate Sanders, chiefly during World War II, 1939-1946 (Box Box 1)
- Personal Papers of Agnes Graham Sanders Riley
  - Membership Applications for Patriotic "Daughter" Organizations, 1966-1973 (Box Box 1)
  - Hollins College, Virginia, 1920-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Kentucky, University of, in Lexington, 1942-1969 (Box Box 1)
  - Personal Papers, 1907-1945 (Box Box 1)
  - Personal Papers, 1970-1990 (Box Box 2)
  - Professional Papers, 1934-1979 (Box Box 2)
- Research Papers of Agnes Graham Sanders Riley
  - Augusta County: Historical Bulletins, 1970, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - William Campbell, 1980-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Robert Graham and descendants, David Graham and David Peirce Graham, 1970-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - William Tate Graham, 1949-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - Graham Family and Property, 1953-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Graham Family and Tate Family Service in Wars, 1961-1989 (Box Box 2)
  - Graham's Magazine, 1844 (Box Box 2)
  - National Genealogical Society--Members' Ancestor Charts for the Graham Family and Sanders Family, 1966-1974 (Box Box 2)
  - Andrew Trigg Sanders, 1942-1988 (Box Box 2)
  - David Graham Sanders, and issue, 1962-1987 (Box Box 2)
  - Edwin Hanson Sanders, 1948-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Edwin Hanson Sanders, Jr., 1924-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Graham Sanders, 1901, 1956-1970 (Box Box 3)
  - Friel Tate Sanders, 1939-1959 (Box Box 3)
  - Southwest Virginia, 1962-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - John Thompson, 1895-1988 (Box Box 3)
  - Trigg Family and related Calhoun Family, 1948-1989 (Box Box 3)
  - Edith Bolling Wilson, 1978-1990 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Churches, 1962-1990 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Early Social Life, 1870, 1977-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Historical Bulletins, 1967-1978 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: "Kegley's Corner", 1983-1989 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Marker to John Montgomery and Descendants, 1938-1965 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Newspaper Articles, 1946-1979 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Newspaper Articles, 1980-1990 (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Newspaper Articles (copies) and other Printed, 1940-1989, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Wythe County: Southwest Virginia Enterprise, Centennial Edition, 1870-1970, 1970 Aug 4 (Box Oversize)